# Uthaipon "Tao" Tantipongpipat

## Machine Learning Engineer / Al Researcher

uthaipon@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/uthaipon/

#### **SUMMARY**

Machine learning engineer and researcher with 4 years of experience after a PhD. Led a team on ML development by planning and executing quarterly milestones in ranking and recommendation systems. Experienced in responsible Al / Al ethics at Twitter. Has driven successful cross-functional projects (resulting in 3+ billions press click-read) and impacted engineers by applying research to set company-wide metrics. Track record (10+) of top-tier peer-reviewed publications in ML, algorithms, and statistics, with emphasis on ML theory, ML fairness, and optimization, with 1st place award from the US government on differential privacy.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Agoda, Bangkok, Thailand - Lead Data Scientist

Jan 2023 - Now

- Implemented and optimized TensorFlow Decision Forest model, and transformed and optimized RNN with attention dataset, improving offline validation metrics by 1-2%.
- Initiated and led a research project to develop a user-specific parameter in the ranking model, integrating customer-loyalty components, resulting in 50% improvement in MSE for predicting customer loyalty and future profit.
- Engineered a CTR (click-through-rate) prediction model, reducing RMSE by 75%. Provided strategic insights to the advertising team for optimizing ad revenue from clicks.
- Designed, implemented, and maintained Scala Spark jobs and SQL alerts for dataset monitoring for models, including anomaly detection and dashboards for trends on user behaviors and devices.
- Managed and strategized with managers, data scientists, and ML engineers on deployment design, decisions, and timelines of the project for the team's milestones.

Twitter, remote US - Machine Learning Researcher

Jun 2020 - Jan 2023

- Led Twitter's image cropping algorithmic bias audit resulting in a published academic paper and \$1.5M press ad equivalency and 3B readership from 500 news articles in 49 countries. Led to another follow-up work by team members resulted in additional \$1.4M, 2.7B reads, and 800 articles from 47 additional countries, and contributed to the decision to remove the algorithm in production.
- Proposed a 13-18% precision-recall video classification model improvement with no additional cost to
  partnering team to fix offensive misclassifications on Tweet topic annotations and discovered correlation
  bias with demographics despite a lack of private individual data.
- Established a data-driven guideline for company-wide engineers to adopt an inequality metric in A/B statistical testing and got business approval from leadership to finally deploy the metric.
- Provided statistical analysis to customer teams to evaluate and quantify bias in ML models; redesigned common ML statistical significance tests required for bias measurement.
- Published two papers in social computing conference and one in data science journal.

- Implemented privacy guarantee on large-scale natural language processing models (RNNs and LSTMs) to protect against personal deidentification due to model usage.
- Researched private correlation clustering algorithm, private submodular optimization, and surveyed literature for private stochastic gradient descent for training deep models.

#### **EDUCATION**

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta GA

Aug 2016 - May 2020

PhD in Algorithms, Combinatorics, and Optimization (ACO). GPA 4.00/4.00

University of Richmond, Richmond VA

Aug 2012 - May 2016

BS in Mathematics, with Thesis (Algebraic Combinatorics). GPA 3.97/4.00

University of Oxford, Oxford UK

Oct 2014 - Jun 2015

Study Abroad Program in Mathematics and Computer Science. First Class.

#### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Measuring Disparate Outcomes of Content Recommendation Algorithms with Distributional Inequality Patterns Journal 2022 Metrics

MathOR 2022; SODA 2019 Volume Sampling and Approximation Algorithms for A-Optimal Design

Image Cropping on Twitter: Fairness Metrics, their Limitations, and the Importance of Representation, Design, and Agency CSCW 2021

NeurIPS 2021

Differentially Private Mixed-Type Data Generation for Unsupervised Learning IISA 2021

Combinatorial Algorithms for Optimal Design

Fast and Memory Efficient Differentially Private-SGD via JL Projections

**COLT 2019** 

The Price of Fair PCA: One Extra Dimension NeurIPS 2018

See Google Scholar https://scholar.google.co.th/citations?hl=th&user=nzO\_5FMAAAAJ for the full list.

### **SELECTED AWARDS**

**Impact Recognition** Award, CSCW (the social computing conference) 2021

2019 **Best Reviewer** of NeurlPS (top-tier machine learning conference)

1st Prize and People's Choice Awards, The Unlinkable Data Challenge, National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST), US Department of Commerce 2018

Honorable Mention (top 2.5%), William Lowell Putnam Mathematical Competition 2015

Bronze Medal and Honorable Mention, Asia-Pacific Mathematics Olympiad (APMO) 2010, 2011

Gold and Bronze Medals, IWYMIC International Mathematics Competition 2008, 2009

#### **SKILLS**

Technical: Python (pandas, numpy, scipy, sklearn), Scala, PySpark, Scala Spark, SQL (BigQuery, Impala), Java,

C++, Tensorflow, PyTorch, Kubeflow, Hadoop, Git, GCP, Superset, Grafana, Mathematica, LaTeX

Languages: Thai (native); English (full proficiency)